A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1972-1976
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1972-1976
The Library of Virginia
1972-1976
11.1 cu. ft. (11 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information available.
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council, as the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. When Whitham took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Most recently, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats on February 22, 1990. The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board.
Wayne A. Whitham, the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety, was reappointed by Governor-elect Miles E. Godwin, Jr., in December 1973 and by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977. Whitham suffered a heart attack in August 1978 and resigned in December 1978. On June 7, 1984, Whitham died in Richmond, Virginia. Governor Dalton named George M. Walters, a former top executive of the Reynolds Metals Corporation, to succeed Whitham as Secretary of Transportation. Walters served until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Andrew B. Fogarty, Dalton's assistant secretary for financial policy, as Secretary of Transportation. On July 1, 1984, the secretariats of transportation and public safety were combined again. As a result this partial reorganization of state government, Governor Robb appointed Fogarty Secretary of Administration and Franklin E. White, Secretary of Public Safety, assumed Fogarty's Transportation duties. White, who served as a White House liaison official under President Jimmy Carter, resigned in June 1985 to become the New York state commissioner of transportation. He was replaced by Andrew Fogarty who served until the end of the Robb administration. He later served as Governor Gerald L. Baliles chief of staff from August 1986 to October 1989 when he resigned to become a vice president with CSX Corporation.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles, picked Vivian E. Watts, a northern Virginia legislator, as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. Watts served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. In 1995 she was elected to her old seat in the Virginia House of Delegates. On February 22, 1990, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats. Governor L. Douglas Wilder, appointed John G. Milliken, a member of the Arlington County Board of Supervisors, as the Secretary of Transportation. Milliken resigned on December 17, 1993.
In February 1994 Governor George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed Robert Martinez as Secretary of Transportation. Martinez was born in Cuba and had served as Deputy Administrator for the Marine Administration and Associate Deputy Secretary of Transportation during President George H.W. Bush's administration. At the end of Governor Allen's term in January 1998, Martinez joined the Norfolk Southern Corporation. Shirley Ybarra, deputy Secretary of Transportation in the Allen administration, was named Martinez's successor by Governor-elect James Gilmore. Ybarra previously worked as a special assistant to Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Dole during President Ronald Reagan's administration. Ybarra served until the end of Gilmore's administration in January 2002. Whittington W. Clement, a former lawyer and long-time member of the Virginia House of Delegates representing the City of Danville, was appointed Secretary of Transportation by Governor Mark R. Warner in 2002. Pierce R. Homer, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, replaced Clement in 2005.
Scope and Content
This collections contains the Secretary of Transportations Summary files related to the Division of State Planning and Community Affairs, the bulk of the collections addresses Virginia's airports, enviromental imapct of transportation, construction contacts, House Joint Resolutions, as well as, transportation studies.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1976., Extent: 1.1 cu. ft. (11 boxes). (Box 1-8)
  The original order of files has been maintained as they were recieved from the agency.
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Planning District Commission Replies, 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - responses, 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Responses (Draft Plan), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study, 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Contract Negotiation), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Federal Guidelines), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Contract and Budget Amendments), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Grant Payments), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Charges against contract/ 3rd Party Contract), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Charges against contract/ State Contribution), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Charges against contract/ Division of Aeronautics), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Charges Against Contract/ Division of Aeronautics), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Financial Reports), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (General Correspondence), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Study Coordination Agreements), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Coordination with Legislative Study Commissions), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Policy Committee), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study - Federal Aviation Administration 116 (Advisory Committees), 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Multi-Regional Air Transportation System Study, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - State In-Kind Study, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Saqmple Letters and Air Carrier Questionaires I, II, III, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Takes I, II, III, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - On-site Survey Procedures and Accompanying Forms, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - In-house Data collection, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Systems Analysis and Research Corporation, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wilber Smith and Associates, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Contract, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Coordination Agreement, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Federal Aviation Administration - Planning Grant, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Air Transportation System Study, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Multi-Regional Air Transportation System Study - Airport Study, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Phase 1, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Phase 2, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - System Study, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Phase 3, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Phase 3, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Phase 3, 1972-1976. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Goals, Objectives, Issues, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Airport Inventory, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Current System Capacity, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Current Environments, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Current Ground Transportation System, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Air Travel Demands, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Aircraft Technology and Characteristics, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Air Space Utilization, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Aircraft noise and the environment part 1, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Aircraft noise and the environment part 2, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Future Ground Transportation System, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Criteria for Evaluation, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Simat, Helliesen and Eichner, Inc., 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Correspondence, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Progress Report and Committee Meetings, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Work Program, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Washington Council of Government Working Papers - Coordination Agreement and Planning Grant, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Maryland Cargo Forecasts, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Maryland Progress Reports and Committee Meetings, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Baltimore/Washington Bi-region Alternative Aviation Systems, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Maryland Working Paper 2, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Maryland - Correspondence, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Maryland - Working Paper 1 Airports and Airspace Inventory, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Maryland - Miscellaneous, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Maryland - Issue Paper 5 Helicopters and Sea Planes, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Maryland - Issue Paper, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Maryland - Enviromental Assessment Report, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Maryland - Airport Choice Model for the Baltimore/Washington B-region, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Maryland - Air Survey, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Maryland - Work Program, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Maryland - Contract with Speas Association, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Maryland - Planning Grant Agreement and Coordination Agreement, 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen, and Bergendoff - Data Transfer, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen, and Bergendoff - Transfer IV, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen, and Bergendoff - General Aviation Forecasts, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen, and Bergendoff - Airport Requirements Computer Program, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Coordinations Agreements, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen, and Bergendoff - Airspace Requirements and System Impacts, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen, and Bergendoff - Airspace and Airport Capacity Summary, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen, and Bergendoff - Air Carrier Operations Forecast, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen, and Bergendoff - Correspondence, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen, and Bergendoff - Air Transportation Technology, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Aviation Transportation and Airport Study Commission, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Maryland Aviation Study, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Central Virginia Planning District Commission, 1972-1976. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Contract and Budget Amendments, 1972-1976. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1972-1976. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Grant Payments, 1972-1976. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Needs Study, 1972-1976. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - National Transportation Needs Study, 1972-1976. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - National Transportation Needs Study - Addendum, 1972-1976. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Loose Papers, 1972-1976. (Box 5)
  - Dues/Subscriptions, 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Washington/Richmond Cooridor Study - Grant Payments, 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Washington/Richmond Cooridor Study - Charges Against Contract, 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Washington/Richmond Cooridor Study - Correspondence, 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Monthly Account Records, 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - House Finance Committee (1 of 4), 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - House Finance Committee (2 of 4), 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - House Finance Committee (3 of 4), 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - House Finance Committee (4 of 4), 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Aviation - Senator Mann's, 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 10-12)
  - Aviation - Senator Mann's (Aviation Subcommittee), 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Aviation - Senator Mann's (Planning, Coordination, Subcommittee), 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Aviation - Senator Mann's (Programs, management and Finance Request Subcommittee), 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Aviation - Senator Mann's (Revenue Subcommittee), 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Metropolitan Areas Transportation Study, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Metropolitan Areas Transportation Study - Commission, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Second Virginia Metropolitan Areas Transportation Study, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Universities Transportation Research Program (3 of 3), 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Transportation Planning and Research Program (2 of 3), 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Transportation Planning and Research Program (1 of 3), 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Department of Transportation grant Programs, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - House Joint Resolution 254, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Washington/Richmond Cooridor Study, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 9-11)
  - T. K. Dyer Contract Payments, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Vehicular Connections, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - House Roads Committee, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen and Bergendoff Contract Payments, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Federal Aviation Administration, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Coordination Agreements, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Contract, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Administrative Correspondence, 1972-1976. (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Old Dominion University, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Madison College, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Polytechnic University and State University, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Reports, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Reports, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Project Proposals, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Project Proposals, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - House Joint Resolution 254 Report - Transportation Source of Air pollution, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - School Bus Study House Joint Resolution 89, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - House Joint Resolution 89 Study Report, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - House Joint Resolution 89 Correspondence, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Guidelines for Implementation of School Bus Legislation, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - House Joint Resolution 89 Arlington County, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - House Joint Resolution 89 Planning District Commission Inputs, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - House Joint Resolution 89 Agency Inputs, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - House Joint Resolution 89 Miscellaneous, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - House Joint Resolution 89 Fairfax County, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Budget Development, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Blue Ridge Air Transportation System Study, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Blue Ridge Air Transportation System Study, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Energy Crisis, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Virginia Air Transportation Study - Management Correspondence, 1972-1976. (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Phase 4, 1972-1976. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Phase 5, 1972-1976. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Phase 6, 1972-1976. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Phase 7, 1972-1976. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Phase 8, 1972-1976. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Application, 1972-1976. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Industry Advisory, 1972-1976. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - State/Local Government Advisory, 1972-1976. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Howard, Needles, Tammen, and Bergendoff, 1972-1976. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Northern Virginia Transit Commission, 1972-1976. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Northern Virginia Transit Commission - Report, 1972-1976. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Northern Virginia Transit Commission - Biennial Budget, 1974-1976. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Draft Plan - Virginia Air Transportation, 1972-1976. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Historica Land Markers Commission, 1972-1976. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Initial Airport Requirements Computer Program Run 1, 1972-1976. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Initial Airport Requirements Computer Program Run 2, 1972-1976. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Maps, 1972-1976. (Box 11)